Guide to the Reginald Moore Sugar Land Convict Leasing System research collection, 1878-2018 MS 636
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Reginald Moore Sugar Land Convict Leasing System research collection
1878-2018
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Moore, Reginald
MS 636
2.5 Linear Feet 6 boxes
0.65 Gigabytes 7 video files of Public Comment portions Sugar Land City Council meetings
Correspondence, reports, research notes, and photographs created and/or maintained by Mr. Reginald Moore, relating to the history of the Convict Leasing System in Sugar Land, Texas and current efforts to publicly recognize that history.
Biographical / Historical
Reginald Moore, of Sugar Land, Texas, has created or maintained this collection of material as part of his work with the Texas Slave Descendants Society. Mr. Moore is an historian and has a certification in Community Economic Development from the College of Biblical Studies. He is also a community activist, and has a particular interest in prison reform and prison re-entry into society. He served as a correctional officer in the Texas Department of Corrections, 1985-1988. Mr. Moore worked in the Beauford H. Jester I and III Units, a prison farm located in unincorporated Fort Bend County, Texas. Jester I Farm was the first built by the state at this site, and was known as the Old Harlem Farm. Although convict leasing as a practice is believed to have begun informally in 1872, the State of Texas sanctioned the contract to lease the penal system to the private firm of Ed H. Cunningham and L.A. Ellis (Cunningham and Ellis) in 1878. In 1883, the land and system reverted from private to state control. While working at this site, Mr. Moore became interested in the history of the Flanagan House (former warden's house) and then in the Central Unit of the prison. Over time, this interest grew and became a major research area for Mr. Moore, who went on to found and chair the Texas Slave Descendants' Society(TSDS) in the early 2000's. Through the TSDS and on his own, Mr. Moore, has worked to gain recognition for the past abuses associated with Sugar Land's convict leasing system. In 2016, the Texas Slave Descendants Society hosted its annual Labor Day program and honored Dr. Ken Brown (University of Houston) with the Emancipator Award for his archaeological work and advocacy in Sugar Land. Dr. Fred McGhee was recognized with the Lifetime Achievement Award. In the previous year, Dr. Lora Wildenthal (Rice University) was honored with the Emancipator Award for leading her students in highlighting Mr. Moore's work through the Houston Area Research Team program.
Mr. Moore serves as a member of the RIP Guardian program for the Imperial Prison Cemetery. Mr. Moore's son, Reginald J. Moore, earned a B.S. in Criminal Justice from Prairie View AM, and has also contributed to this body of research.
Texas Monthly magazine featured Mr. Moore and his advocacy regarding convict leasing in the January 2017 issue, available online at http://www.texasmonthly.com/articles/sugar-land-slave-convict-labor-history/. In Summer 2017, construction began on the Sugar Land Heritage Museum and Visitor Center, with the City of Sugar Land and the Sugar Land Heritage Foundation as partners in its creation. The museum and visitor center are set to open by the end of 2017. Mr. Moore and the Texas Slave Descendants Society has lobbied since 2003 for a separate museum and monument to tell the story of convict leasing and black history, within the context of Fort Bend County history.
In 2018, unmarked graves in the vicinity of the Imperial Prison Cemetery were discovered when the land was being being developed for Fort Bend ISD's future technology center.
Fox 26 News story, "Mystery deepens over unmarked Sugar Land cemetery on Ft. Bend school site" April 13, 2018 http://www.fox26houston.com/news/mystery-deepens-over-unmarked-sugar-land-cemetery-on-site-of-ft-bend-school-project
KTRK ABC News story: "Historic cemetery found on construction site of Fort Bend ISD's future technology center" April 11, 2018: http://abc13.com/society/historic-cemetery-found-on-ft-bend-isd-work-site/3329602/
KTRK ABC News story: "89 graves found at construction site of Fort Bend ISD's new technology center" April 25, 2018 http://abc13.com/society/89-graves-found-at-site-of-fort-bend-isds-new-technology-center/3392447/
Content Description
Correspondence, reports, research notes, and photographs created and/or maintained by Mr. Reginald Moore, relating to the history of the Convict Leasing System in Sugar Land, Texas and current efforts to publicly recognize that history. The reports included in this collection are in some cases publicly available, but are difficult to access. Correspondence includes letters and emails between Mr. Moore and various public officials and other interested parties such as archaeologist Fred McGhee.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated by Reginald Moore in 2015-2018.
Reginald Moore can be contacted by phone.
To contact him, please provide your phone number to the staff at the Woodson Research Center, at woodson@rice.edu or 713-348-2586. The staff will provide your request to Mr. Moore, in accordance with our donor privacy policy. Thank you very much.
Related Materials
An exhibit featuring this material has been created by Rice Univesity students as part of a Houston Area Research Team project in July 2015 under the leadership of Dr. Lora Wildenthal. See the exhibit online at http://exhibits.library.rice.edu/exhibits/show/sugarlandconvictleasing/about.
A physical exhibit called "Convict Leasing in Sugar Land: Featuring the Research Collection of Reginald Moore" was created and displayed at Rice University's Fondren Library in December 2015. This display coincided with the 150th anniversary of the 1865 13th Amendment to the Constitution. A news story in video format is available online at https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fC6dsIE-mY8.
Additional archival materials relating to Reginald Moore's community activism are located the African American Library at the Gregory School, in Houston, Texas, http://www.thegregoryschool.org/collection.html.
Related Materials
News coverage of these 2018 findings, and more are listed at https://exhibits.library.rice.edu/exhibits/show/sugarlandconvictleasing/bodies-found-2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Civil rights; Slavery; Prisoners -- Texas -- History; Convict labor -- Texas; Prisoners and prisons; African Americans; Agriculture
Document Types
reports; letters (correspondence); Maps; notes; clippings (information artifacts)
Places
Sugar Land, Tex.
Subjects (Persons)
Moore, Reginald
Subjects (Corporations)
Convict Labor and Leasing Project
- Series I: Background
  - Convict leasing background (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sugar Land background (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reginald Moore biographical sketch (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Note fragments from Reginald Moore (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flanagan House background (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Archaeology (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes "An Archeological Survey of the Proposed Brazos River Corridor Park (Phase 1), City of Sugar Land, Fort Bend County, Texas, Texas Antiquities Permit No. 3383" May 2004, by Moore Archeological Consulting Inc.
  - Texas Slave Descendants Society notes and letters (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Texas Slave Descendants Society letterhead samples (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Texas Slave Descendants Society packet regarding Imperial Char House, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Texas Slave Descendants Society packet regarding Central State Prison Farm, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Site assessment for 96 acres at Hwy 6 and Hwy 90A, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Fred McGhee, archaeologist, correspondence, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - City of Sugar Land correspondence regarding bond election and public testimony (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Texas Historical Commission, including June 25, 2013 letter of support regarding recognition efforts for convict leasing system, written to City of Sugar Land (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    General
    Also includes correspondence regarding historical marker at Old Imperial Farm Cemetery and list of tombstone inscriptions in that cemetery.
    - Correspondence regarding historical marker at Old Imperial Farm Cemetery and list of tombstone inscriptions in that cemetery
    - Newland Communities survey correspondence, 2002-2004
    - Newland Communities, Notice of Application regarding standard permit, Permit 23235, Nov. 2003
    - Aliana Development Co. Wetland Development Mitigation Plan 2006
    - Newland Communities Permit Application 23235: Environmental Assessment and Statement of Findings, 2004
    - Newland Communities Permit Application 23252 Proposed Site Development Wetland Overlay Map and related correspondence, 2004-2007
    - City of Sugar Land correspondence with Texas Historical Commission regarding sale of Central Prison Unit in Fort Bend County, 2013
    - Texas Historical Commission RIP Cemetery Guardian program correspondence with Reginald Moore, 2010
    - THC correspondence with Reginald Moore regarding concerns about possible additional graves on Central Prison Unit tracts 4 and 5, 2006
  - City of Sugar Land, regarding Lonnie Green Park, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Texas Historical Commission, agendas and recordings on CD, January 2016 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Texas Historical Commission, audio recording October 2016 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Texas Historical Commission, 2017 correspondence regarding archaeological review of site for James Reese Career and Technology Center (Fort Bend ISD) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fort Bend ISD and Goshawk Environmental Consulting correspondence regarding prisoners' bodies found in unmarked graves, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - State of Texas political representatives, 2013-2014 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes December 2014 letter from the office of Texas Senator Joan Huffman acknowledging receipt of Mr. Moore's fax and phone calls; December 2014 letter from the office of the Texas Senate Criminal Justice Committee including Senator John Whitmire and Senator Joan Huffman, thanking Mr. Moore for his recent letter requesting an apology from the state regarding the convict leasing system. Also includes a letter from Mr. Moore dated October 2013, to Ms. Dede Keith of the Office of the Governor (Rick Perry) requesting an apology from the state regarding the convict leasing system.The Governor's office suggests working with the Texas Historical COmmission on this issue.
  - Texas General Land Office, 2007-2013 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    2007 correspondence regarding whether the Old Imperial Farm Cemetery is in the Battle or Hodge League survey, and a copy of the 2001 "Archaeological Reconnaisance of High Probability Areas in the Texas Department of Criminal Justice Harlem Prison Farm Tract, Fort Bend, County, Texas," as well as a copy of the "Historic American Building Survey Texas Central State Prison Farm, Central 2 Camp HABS No. TX-"; and 2013 correspondence regarding what would be required by the Texas Antiquities Code if the General Land Office sold the Central Unit prison lands.
  - Texas Department of Criminal Justice, map of Central Unit's Historic Sites and Boundaries (undated) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Texas Board of Criminal Justice, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Letter from Oliver Bell of the Texas Board of Criminal Justice, to Mark Wolfe, of the Texas Historical Commission, regarding the sale over time of parts of the Central Unit lands, and that the General Land Office will conduct sales in accordance with "all applicable statutory requirements pertaining to the protection of state archaeological antiquities."
  - Save Texas Cemeteries, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - University of Houston Sugar Land campus correspondence, 2013-2014 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Texas Interfaith Center for Public Policy, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Texas Holocaust and Genocide Commission, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Letter of response to Mr. Moore stating that the Texas Holocaust and Genocide Commission contacted Sen. Joan Huffman's office regarding the convict leasing system.
  - Rice University, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Texas Criminal Justice Coalition, including Jay Jenkins, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 9a)
    Correspondence documenting initial contact between Mr. Moore and TCJC.
- Series III: Resolutions and Awards
  - First Annual Juneteenth and Abolitionist Recognition Day in Sugar Land, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Old Imperial Black Prison Cemetery Preservation and Historical Society honored for its commitment to preserving the heritage of this state and its people, by Dora Olivo, State Rep. District 27 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Emancipator Awards, 2013-2015 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Biographical / Historical
    The Emancipaptor Award is an annual Labor Day Recognition of the Convict Lease System, presented to a deserving community member by the Texas Slave Descendants Society.
    - Texas State Rep. Dora Olivo, 2013
    - Patty Sayes, 2014
    - Dr. Lora Wildenthal, Rice University, 2015
- Series IV: Newsclippings
  - Newsclippings, including Summer 2017 news article regarding creation of Sugar Land Heritage Museum and Visitor Center, 2004-2017 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newsclippings regarding discovery of 95 unmarked prisoner graves, 2018 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Published reports
  - Biennial Report of the Directors and Superintendent of the Texas State Penitentiary (photocopy), 1878-1880 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Texas Department of Criminal Justice, Central Unit Main Building and its Historical Significance, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Texas Central Prison State Farm, Central 2 Camp, HABS No. TX- ___ (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bob Skiles report on Central State Prison Farm (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Hell Hole on the Brazos, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jaybird Woodpecker War research and notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Brazoria County convict leasing research from the Brazoria County Historical Museum, including Lake Jackson Plantation (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Mexican American War in my own words, by Reginald Jeremy Moore, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Photographs from Texas State Library and Archives (digital and print) (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Series VII: Video of public testimony regarding bond election, 2006-2013
  Conditions Governing Access
  Video content to processed as AIP, Summer 2017. (asf format to mp4 in handbrake software, Z:\Video\ReginaldMoore-HART-2015)
  - Sugar Land City Council testimony and public comment. Dates: Feb. 21, 2006; July 16, 2013; August 06, 2013;August 20, 2013. Topic: park bond proposal regarding legacy of convict leasing in that area, requesting a memorial of some kind and/ or a museum in the park area., 2006-2013
- Series VIII: Community events, publicity and speaking, 2013-2018
  - Black Panthers background and note of Reginald Moore's comments on radio shows (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Event: 1st Annual Juneteenth Celebration / Abolitionist Day Recognition program (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Events: 1st Annual Labor Day Recognition program, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Events: Labor Day Festival / Texas Slave Descendants Society program, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Television show "The Dead Files" featuring prison farm in Lake Jackson, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 13a)
  - Event: 4th Annual Labor Day Recognition event program "Where Do We Go from Here?" flyers, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Event: 4th Annual Labor Day Recognition event program "Where Do We Go from Here?" audio recording of speeches (4 hours, 7 minutes), 2016
    Filename MLK-event-2016-speeches.MP3
  - Event: 5th Annual Labor Day Recognition event program "Where Do We Go from Here?" video recording of speeches, 2015
  - Regarding Ava DuVernay's film project"13th" on Netflix, Reginald Moore's comments on radio show Democracy Now, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence regarding film project by Alex Johnston "A Natural Death" 2015 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Article on Reginald Moore by Texas Monthly magazine, "Blood and Sugar" January 2017 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Radio call-in show transcription, "Prison Show," KPFT, Nov. 6, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Event: Moore speaking at Women Empowerment Training Institute, on free labor having built Sugar Land, certificate and images, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - KPRC news coverage of 2016 MLK event organized by Reginald Moore (audio recording of tv news), Sept. 5, 2016
    Filename MLK-event2016-KPRCnews.MP3
  - KFPT Houston radio talk show recording regarding slavery and MLK (7 minutes 42 seconds)
    Filename KPFT-radio-undated.mp3
  - C-SPAN interview, Reginald Moore calling in regarding reparations for slavery and other crimes against African-Americans, audio (6 minutes 42 seconds), 2017-11-13
    Filename C_SPAN-call-in-2017.MP3
  - C-SPAN interview, Reginald Moore calling in regarding budget priorities, defense spending when social security needs attention to help the poor (3 minutes, 23 seconds), 2017-02-28
    Filename C-SPAN-Feb29-2017.MP3
  - C-SPAN call-in regarding MLK, the Poor People's Campaign (2 minutes and 39 seconds), 2017-04-04
    Related Materials
    Filename C-SPAN-April4-2017.MP3
  - Texas Historical Commission public meetings recording, January 2016
    Full commission meeting, as well as Antiquities Advisory Board, Archaeology committee, Architecture committee, and more. Mr. Moore was present and recorded the audio.
  - Radio call-in show regarding lynching museum, 2018-05-20
    Does not feature Mr. Moore talking, but is a recording of a call-in show about the lynching museum. Filename May20-2018-lynching-museum.MP3
  - Fort Bend County hearing on whether county would be able to exhume bodies found, 2018-06-04
    Hearing on whether Fort Bend County would be able to exhume the bodies found, with Ken Brown, Richard Vogel, describing meeting and a recording of a news story about it that day. File name = June-4-2018-FortBend.MP3
  - John de la Cruz, talking on the phone about San Isidro Cemetery, 2018-05-11
    File name = May11-2018-SanIsidroCemetery.MP3
  - Diana Hernandez and Reginald Moore walking the Scanlan Plantation site, and talking, 2018-05-06
    Driving and walking interview with Mr. Moore and Diana Hernandez, looking at a church and cemetery. File name = Hernandez-tour-SanIsidroCemetery-part1.MP3
  - Diana Hernandez and Reginald Moore, walking Scanlan Plantation site, part 2, 2018-05-06
    Driving and walking interview with Mr. Moore and Diana Hernandez, looking at a church and cemetery File name = Hernandez-tour-SanIsidroCemetery-part2.MP3
  - Tom Hartman show on Free Speech TV speaking on book called Discover, Mr. Moore calling in about the prisoner graves found in Fort Bend County, 2018-05-03
    File name = May3-2018-TomHartman-show.MP3
  - Democracy Now call in show - Brian Stevenson on Equal Justice Initiative / Slave Museum in Montgomery Alabama, 2018-05-01
    File name = May1-2018-SlaveMuseum-Alabama.mp3
  - Channel 13 Fort Bend County graves found TV news segment, 2018-04-26
    File name = Apr26-2018-tvnews-graves.mp3
  - Fort Bend County finding graves - petition for social justice - Channel 39 9pm tv news segment, including Mr. Moore speaking, 2018-04-23
    File name = Apr23-2018-79graves.mp3
  - Recorded conversation, unidentified people, topics include privatizing prisons / current prison problems and drugs / convict leasing history, 2018
    File name = 2018-prison-problems-conversation.mp3
  - Jose Grinon on Fox 26 5:45am tv news coverage featuring Mr. Moore, Melissa Thibodeaux, Ken Brown, about graves found on prison grounds in Fort Bend County, 2018-04-13
    File name = April-13-2018-tv-newsFox26.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 11 tv, 2018-04-12
    File name = April12-2018-tvnews-graves-Channel11.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 11 tv, featuring Mr. Moore and Dr. Ken Brown, 2018-04-11
    File name = April11-2018-tvnews-graves-Channel11.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 11, 2018-04-11
    File name = April11-2018-tvnews-graves-Ch11.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 13, featuring Mr. Moore, 2018-04-11
    File name = April11-2018-tvnewsCh13-5pm.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 11, 2018-04-10
    File name = April-10-2018-Ch11news-graves.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 2, Mr. Moore speaking on unmarked graves discovered, 2018-04-10
    File name April-10-2018-Ch2-MrMoore-graves.mp3
  - News audio, Channel 13, 2018-04-09
    File name = April-9-2018-Ch13-22graves.mp3
  - Texas State Board of Education public testimony, Mr. Moore regarding convict leasing not prominent enough in Texas history textbooks, 2018-09-11
    File name = RegMoore-9-11-2018-State-Board-education.m4a
- Series IX: Community events, publicity, speaking regarding discovery of prisoners' bodies, 2018
  - Correspondence, event flyers, news clippings, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Event flyers, news clippings, 2019 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Texas Historical Commission correspondence with Mr. Moore, summarizing the sequence of events and Mr. Moore's advocacy steps as understood by THC, as well as a description of the now defunct RIP Guardian program for cemeteries, 2019 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Video of speaking event at Harvard University, "Unearthing the truth, Sugar Land, TX", 2019-03-11
    You Tube video of streamed event https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=97&v=LDYZe9d_uW4
  - Where Do We Go From Here? Memorial Day event honoring the Sugar Land 95, 2018-05
  - Where Do We Go From Here? MLK Jr. event organized by Reginald Moore, focused on the Poverty Report, at Martin Luther King, Jr. Center, 3611 Ennis St. Houston TX, 2018-04-04
  - Reginald Moore touring Jack Yates High School and neighborhood, 2018-07
  - Clip of Democracy Now television show, featuring the Lynching Museum opening, 2018-05-01
    Reginald Moore collected this clip but does not feature in it.
- Series X: Additional Sugar Land and Fort Bend County background
  - Sugar Land news clippings and background (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Newsclippings
    - Report: "Texas Oldest Cane Sugar Refinery" by Bettye J. Anhaiser for the Texas Historical Commission, 1976-1977
    - Imperial Redevelopment Project, Sugar Land, TX, Pattern Book, by Southern Land Company LLC, March 2008
    - Sugar Land and Central State Farm History article, by Allen Bogard
  - Slavery in Texas background (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Slavery in the Republic of Texas" thesis by Linda Myers Purcell, UNT, May 1982
      Research copy photocopy of thesis, obtained from Brazoria County Historical Museum
    - "Slavery in Early Texas," Political Science Quarterly, September 1898
    - "Management of Negroes upon Southern Estates" Debow's review, Agricultural, commercial, industrial progress and resources. Volume 10, Issue 6, June 1851, pp. 621-627
    - "Slavery in Houston: The 1850s" by Susan Jackson, Summer 1980 (publication name illegible)
    - "The African Slave Trade in Texas," by Eugene C. Barker, Texas Historical Association Quarterly
  - Walter Moss Burton historical marker documentation, Fort Bend County, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reginald Moore's annotated copy of "Two Glass Buttons: A Story of the Runaway Scrape," by Marguerite Starr Crain (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Report: "The Impact of Community Violence on African American Children and Families" by Maternal and Child Health Bureau (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Printed copy of pamphlet "The Reason Why The Colored American Is Not in the World's Columbian Exposition" (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Partial photocopy of book "The Willie Lynch Letter and the Making of a Slave" by William Lynch (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series XI: Addendum of materials released after the death of Reginald Moore